<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on alexandru topliceanu</title>
    <link>http://alexandrutopliceanu.ro/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on alexandru topliceanu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 08:53:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://alexandrutopliceanu.ro/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>graphql with go and postgresql</title>
      <link>http://alexandrutopliceanu.ro/post/graphql-with-go-and-postgresql/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 08:53:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexandrutopliceanu.ro/post/graphql-with-go-and-postgresql/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;graphql-in-use-building-a-blogging-engine-api-with-golang-and-postgresql&#34;&gt;GraphQL In Use: Building a Blogging Engine API with Golang and PostgreSQL&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraphQL appears hard to use in production: the graph interface is flexible in its modeling capabilities but is a poor match for relational storage, both in terms of implementation and performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this document, we will design and write a simple blogging engine api, with three types of resources (users, posts and comments) and a varied set of functionality (create a user, create a post, add a comment to a post, follow posts and comments from another user, etc.), use PostgreSQL as the backing datastore (chosen because it&amp;rsquo;s a popular relational DB) and write the API implementation in golang (a popular language for writing APIs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will compare a simple GraphQL implementation with a pure REST alternative in terms of implementation complexity and efficiency for a common scenario: rendering a blog post page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraphQL is an IDL (Interface Definition Language), designers define data types and model information as a graph. Each vertex is an instance of a data type, while edges represent relationships between nodes. This approach if flexible and can accommodate any business domain. However, the problem is that the design process is more involved and traditional data stores don&amp;rsquo;t map well to the graph model. See &lt;em&gt;Appendix 1&lt;/em&gt; for more details on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraphQL has been first proposed in 2014 by the Facebook Engineering Team. Although interesting and compelling in it&amp;rsquo;s advantages and features, it hasn&amp;rsquo;t seen mass adoption. Developers have to trade REST&amp;rsquo;s simplicity of design, familiarity and rich tooling for GraphQL&amp;rsquo;s flexibility of not being limited to just CRUD and network efficiency (it optimizes for round-trips to the server).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most walkthroughs and tutorials on GraphQL avoid the problem of fetching data from the datastore to resolve queries. That is, how to design a database, using general-purpose, popular storage solutions (like relational databases) to support efficient data retrieval in a GraphQL API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document goes through building a blog engine GraphQL API. It is moderately complex in it&amp;rsquo;s functionality. It is scoped to a familiar business domain to facilitate comparisons with a REST based approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of this document is the following:
* in the first part we will design a GraphQL schema and explain some of features of the language that are used.
* next is the design of the postgresql database in section two.
* part three covers the golang implementation of the GraphQL schema designed in part one.
* in part four we compare the task of rendering a blog post page from the perspective of fetching the needed data from the backend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;related&#34;&gt;Related&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://graphql.org/learn/&#34;&gt;GraphQL introduction document&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The complete and working code for this project is on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topliceanu/graphql-go-example&#34;&gt;github.com/topliceanu/graphql-go-example&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;modeling-a-blog-engine-in-graphql&#34;&gt;Modeling a blog engine in GraphQL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Listing 1&lt;/em&gt; contains the entire schema for the blog engine api. It shows the data types of the vertices composing the graph. The relationships between vertices, ie. the edges, are modeled as attributes of a given type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-graphql&#34;&gt;type User {
  id: ID
  email: String!
  post(id: ID!): Post
  posts: [Post!]!
  follower(id: ID!): User
  followers: [User!]!
  followee(id: ID!): User
  followees: [User!]!
}

type Post {
  id: ID
  user: User!
  title: String!
  body: String!
  comment(id: ID!): Comment
  comments: [Comment!]!
}

type Comment {
  id: ID
  user: User!
  post: Post!
  title: String
  body: String!
}

type Query {
  user(id: ID!): User
}

type Mutation {
  createUser(email: String!): User
  removeUser(id: ID!): Boolean
  follow(follower: ID!, followee: ID!): Boolean
  unfollow(follower: ID!, followee: ID!): Boolean
  createPost(user: ID!, title: String!, body: String!): Post
  removePost(id: ID!): Boolean
  createComment(user: ID!, post: ID!, title: String!, body: String!): Comment
  removeComment(id: ID!): Boolean
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Listing 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The schema is written in the GraphQL DSL, which is used for defining custom data types, such as &lt;code&gt;User&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Post&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Comment&lt;/code&gt;. A set of primitive data types is also provided by the language, such as &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Boolean&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ID&lt;/code&gt; (which is an alias of &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt; with the additional semantics of being the unique identifier of a vertex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Query&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Mutation&lt;/code&gt; are optional types recognized by the parser and used in querying the graph. Reading data from a GraphQL API is equivalent to traversing the graph. As such a starting vertex needs to be provided, this role is fulfilled by the &lt;code&gt;Query&lt;/code&gt; type. In this case, all queries to the graph must start with a user specified by id &lt;code&gt;user(id:ID!)&lt;/code&gt;. For writing data, the &lt;code&gt;Mutation&lt;/code&gt; vertex type is defined. This exposes a set of operations, modeled as parameterized attributes which traverse to (and return) the newly created vertex types. See &lt;em&gt;Listing 2&lt;/em&gt; for examples of how these queries might look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vertex attributes can be parameterized, ie. accept arguments. In the context of graph traversal, if a post vertex has multiple comment vertices, you can traverse to just one of them by specifying &lt;code&gt;comment(id: ID)&lt;/code&gt;. All this is by design, the designer can choose not to provide direct paths to individual vertices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt; character is a type post-fix, works for both primitive or user-defined types and has two semantics:
 * when used for the type of a param in a parametriezed attribute, it means that param is required.
 * when used for the return type of an attribute it means that attribute will not be null when the vertex is retrieved.
 * combinations are possible, for instance &lt;code&gt;[Comment!]!&lt;/code&gt; represents a list of non-null Comment vertices, where &lt;code&gt;[]&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;[Comment]&lt;/code&gt; are valid, but &lt;code&gt;null, [null], [Comment, null]&lt;/code&gt; are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Listing 2&lt;/em&gt; contains a list of curl commands against the blogging api which will populate the graph using mutations and then query it to retrieve data. To run them, follow the instructions in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topliceanu/graphql-go-example&#34;&gt;topliceanu/graphql-go-example&lt;/a&gt; repo to build and run the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;# Mutations to create users 1,2 and 3. Mutations also work as queries, in these case we retrieve the ids and emails of the newly created users.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {createUser(email:&amp;quot;user1@x.co&amp;quot;){id, email}}&#39;
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {createUser(email:&amp;quot;user2@x.co&amp;quot;){id, email}}&#39;
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {createUser(email:&amp;quot;user3@x.co&amp;quot;){id, email}}&#39;
# Mutations to add posts for the users. We retrive their ids to comply with the schema, otherwise we will get an error.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {createPost(user:1,title:&amp;quot;post1&amp;quot;,body:&amp;quot;body1&amp;quot;){id}}&#39;
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {createPost(user:1,title:&amp;quot;post2&amp;quot;,body:&amp;quot;body2&amp;quot;){id}}&#39;
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {createPost(user:2,title:&amp;quot;post3&amp;quot;,body:&amp;quot;body3&amp;quot;){id}}&#39;
# Mutations to all comments to posts. `createComment` expects the user&#39;s ID a title and a body. See the schema in Listing 1.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {createComment(user:2,post:1,title:&amp;quot;comment1&amp;quot;,body:&amp;quot;comment1&amp;quot;){id}}&#39;
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {createComment(user:1,post:3,title:&amp;quot;comment2&amp;quot;,body:&amp;quot;comment2&amp;quot;){id}}&#39;
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {createComment(user:3,post:3,title:&amp;quot;comment3&amp;quot;,body:&amp;quot;comment3&amp;quot;){id}}&#39;
# Mutations to have the user3 follow users 1 and 2. Note that the `follow` mutation only returns a boolean which doesn&#39;t need to be specified.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {follow(follower:3, followee:1)}&#39;
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;mutation {follow(follower:3, followee:2)}&#39;

# Query to fetch all data for user 1
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;{user(id:1)}&#39;
# Queries to fetch the followers of user2 and, respectively, user1.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;{user(id:2){followers{id, email}}}&#39;
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;{user(id:1){followers{id, email}}}&#39;
# Query to check if user2 is being followed by user1. If so retrieve user1&#39;s email, otherwise return null.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;{user(id:2){follower(id:1){email}}}&#39;
# Query to return ids and email for all the users being followed by user3.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;{user(id:3){followees{id, email}}}&#39;
# Query to retrive the email of user3 if it is being followed by user1.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;{user(id:1){followee(id:3){email}}}&#39;
# Query to fetch user1&#39;s post2 and retrieve the title and body. If post2 was not created by user1, null will be returned.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;{user(id:1){post(id:2){title,body}}}&#39;
# Query to retrieve all data about all the posts of user1.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;{user(id:1){posts{id,title,body}}}&#39;
# Query to retrive the user who wrote post2, if post2 was written by user1; a contrived example by displays the flexibility of the language.
curl -XPOST http://vm:8080/graphql -d &#39;{user(id:1){post(id:2){user{id,email}}}}&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Listing 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By carefully desiging the mutations and type attributes, powerfull and expressive queries are possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;designing-the-postgresql-database&#34;&gt;Designing the PostgreSQL database&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relational database design is, as usual, driven by the need to avoid data duplication.This approach was chosen for two reasons:
 1. to show that there is no need for a specialized database technology or to learn and use new design techniques to accommodate a GraphQL API.
 2. to show that a GraphQL API can still be created on top of existing databases, more specifically databases designed to back REST endpoints or even traditional server-side rendered html websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;em&gt;Appendix 1&lt;/em&gt; for a discussion on differences between relational and graph databases with respect to building a GraphQL API. &lt;em&gt;Listing 3&lt;/em&gt; shows the SQL commands to create the new database. The database schema generally matches the GraphQL schema. The &lt;code&gt;followers&lt;/code&gt; relation needed to be added to support the &lt;code&gt;follow/unfollow&lt;/code&gt; mutations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sql&#34;&gt;CREATE TABLE IF NOT EXISTS users (
  id SERIAL PRIMARY KEY,
  email VARCHAR(100) NOT NULL
);
CREATE TABLE IF NOT EXISTS posts (
  id SERIAL PRIMARY KEY,
  user_id INTEGER NOT NULL REFERENCES users(id) ON DELETE CASCADE,
  title VARCHAR(200) NOT NULL,
  body TEXT NOT NULL
);
CREATE TABLE IF NOT EXISTS comments (
  id SERIAL PRIMARY KEY,
  user_id INTEGER NOT NULL REFERENCES users(id) ON DELETE CASCADE,
  post_id INTEGER NOT NULL REFERENCES posts(id) ON DELETE CASCADE,
  title VARCHAR(200) NOT NULL,
  body TEXT NOT NULL
);
CREATE TABLE IF NOT EXISTS followers (
  follower_id INTEGER NOT NULL REFERENCES users(id) ON DELETE CASCADE,
  followee_id INTEGER NOT NULL REFERENCES users(id) ON DELETE CASCADE,
  PRIMARY KEY(follower_id, followee_id)
);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Listing 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;golang-api-implementation&#34;&gt;Golang API Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graphql parser implemented in go and used in this project is &lt;code&gt;github.com/graphql-go/graphql&lt;/code&gt;. It contains a query parser, but no schema parser. This requires the programer to build the GraphQL schema in go using the constructs offered by the library. This is unlike the reference &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/graphql/graphql-js&#34;&gt;nodejs implementation&lt;/a&gt;, which offers a schema parser and exposes hooks for data fetching. As such the schema in &lt;code&gt;Listing 1&lt;/code&gt; is only useful as a guideline and has to be translated into golang code. However, this &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;limitation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; offers the opportunity to peer behind the levels of abstraction and see how the schema relates to the graph traversal model for retrieving data. &lt;em&gt;Listing 4&lt;/em&gt; shows the implementation of the &lt;code&gt;Comment&lt;/code&gt; vertex type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;var CommentType = graphql.NewObject(graphql.ObjectConfig{
	Name: &amp;quot;Comment&amp;quot;,
	Fields: graphql.Fields{
		&amp;quot;id&amp;quot;: &amp;amp;graphql.Field{
			Type: graphql.NewNonNull(graphql.ID),
			Resolve: func(p graphql.ResolveParams) (interface{}, error) {
				if comment, ok := p.Source.(*Comment); ok == true {
					return comment.ID, nil
				}
				return nil, nil
			},
		},
		&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;: &amp;amp;graphql.Field{
			Type: graphql.NewNonNull(graphql.String),
			Resolve: func(p graphql.ResolveParams) (interface{}, error) {
				if comment, ok := p.Source.(*Comment); ok == true {
					return comment.Title, nil
				}
				return nil, nil
			},
		},
		&amp;quot;body&amp;quot;: &amp;amp;graphql.Field{
			Type: graphql.NewNonNull(graphql.ID),
			Resolve: func(p graphql.ResolveParams) (interface{}, error) {
				if comment, ok := p.Source.(*Comment); ok == true {
					return comment.Body, nil
				}
				return nil, nil
			},
		},
	},
})
func init() {
	CommentType.AddFieldConfig(&amp;quot;user&amp;quot;, &amp;amp;graphql.Field{
		Type: UserType,
		Resolve: func(p graphql.ResolveParams) (interface{}, error) {
			if comment, ok := p.Source.(*Comment); ok == true {
				return GetUserByID(comment.UserID)
			}
			return nil, nil
		},
	})
	CommentType.AddFieldConfig(&amp;quot;post&amp;quot;, &amp;amp;graphql.Field{
		Type: PostType,
		Args: graphql.FieldConfigArgument{
			&amp;quot;id&amp;quot;: &amp;amp;graphql.ArgumentConfig{
				Description: &amp;quot;Post ID&amp;quot;,
				Type:        graphql.NewNonNull(graphql.ID),
			},
		},
		Resolve: func(p graphql.ResolveParams) (interface{}, error) {
			i := p.Args[&amp;quot;id&amp;quot;].(string)
			id, err := strconv.Atoi(i)
			if err != nil {
				return nil, err
			}
			return GetPostByID(id)
		},
	})
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Listing 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like in the schema in &lt;em&gt;Listing 1&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;code&gt;Comment&lt;/code&gt; type is a structure with three attributes defined statically; &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;title&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;body&lt;/code&gt;. Two other attributes &lt;code&gt;user&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;comment&lt;/code&gt; are defined dynamically to avoid circular dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go does not lend itself well to this kind of dynamic modelling, there is little type checking support, most of the variables in the code are of type &lt;code&gt;interface{}&lt;/code&gt; and need to be type asserted. &lt;code&gt;CommentType&lt;/code&gt; itself is a varible of type &lt;code&gt;graphql.Object&lt;/code&gt; and it&amp;rsquo;s attributes are of type &lt;code&gt;graphql.Field&lt;/code&gt;. So, there&amp;rsquo;s not direct translation between the GraphQL DSL and the data structures used in go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;resolve&lt;/code&gt; function for each field exposes the &lt;code&gt;Source&lt;/code&gt; parameter which is a data type vertex representing the previous node in the traversal. All the attributes of a &lt;code&gt;Comment&lt;/code&gt; have, as source, the current &lt;code&gt;CommentType&lt;/code&gt; vertex. Retrieving the &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;title&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;body&lt;/code&gt; are straightforward attribute accessors, while retrieving the &lt;code&gt;user&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;post&lt;/code&gt; require graph traversals, and thus database queries. The SQL queries are left out of this document because of their simplicity, but they are available in github repository listed in the references section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparison-with-rest-in-common-scenarios&#34;&gt;Comparison with REST in common scenarios&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section we will present a common blog page rendering scenario and compare the REST and the GraphQL implementations. The focus will be on the number of inbound/outbound requests, because these are the biggest contributors to the latency of rendering the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scenario: render a blog post page. It should contain information about the author (email), about the blog post (title, body), all comments (title, body) and whether the user that made the comment follows the author of the blog post or not. &lt;em&gt;Figure 1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Figure 2&lt;/em&gt; show the interaction between the client SPA, the API server and the database, for a REST API and, respectively, for a GraphQL API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+------+                  +------+                  +--------+
|client|                  |server|                  |database|
+--+---+                  +--+---+                  +----+---+
   |      GET /blogs/:id     |                           |
1. +-------------------------&amp;gt;  SELECT * FROM blogs...   |
   |                         +---------------------------&amp;gt;
   |                         &amp;lt;---------------------------+
   &amp;lt;-------------------------+                           |
   |                         |                           |
   |     GET /users/:id      |                           |
2. +-------------------------&amp;gt;  SELECT * FROM users...   |
   |                         +---------------------------&amp;gt;
   |                         &amp;lt;---------------------------+
   &amp;lt;-------------------------+                           |
   |                         |                           |
   | GET /blogs/:id/comments |                           |
3. +-------------------------&amp;gt; SELECT * FROM comments... |
   |                         +---------------------------&amp;gt;
   |                         &amp;lt;---------------------------+
   &amp;lt;-------------------------+                           |
   |                         |                           |
   | GET /users/:id/followers|                           |
4. +-------------------------&amp;gt; SELECT * FROM followers.. |
   |                         +---------------------------&amp;gt;
   |                         &amp;lt;---------------------------+
   &amp;lt;-------------------------+                           |
   |                         |                           |
   +                         +                           +
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+------+                  +------+                  +--------+
|client|                  |server|                  |database|
+--+---+                  +--+---+                  +----+---+
   |      GET /graphql       |                           |
1. +-------------------------&amp;gt;  SELECT * FROM blogs...   |
   |                         +---------------------------&amp;gt;
   |                         &amp;lt;---------------------------+
   |                         |                           |
   |                         |                           |
   |                         |                           |
2. |                         |  SELECT * FROM users...   |
   |                         +---------------------------&amp;gt;
   |                         &amp;lt;---------------------------+
   |                         |                           |
   |                         |                           |
   |                         |                           |
3. |                         | SELECT * FROM comments... |
   |                         +---------------------------&amp;gt;
   |                         &amp;lt;---------------------------+
   |                         |                           |
   |                         |                           |
   |                         |                           |
4. |                         | SELECT * FROM followers.. |
   |                         +---------------------------&amp;gt;
   |                         &amp;lt;---------------------------+
   &amp;lt;-------------------------+                           |
   |                         |                           |
   +                         +                           +
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Listing 5&lt;/em&gt; contains the single GraphQL query which will fetch all the data needed to render the blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-graphql&#34;&gt;{
  user(id: 1) {
    email
    followers
    post(id: 1) {
      title
      body
      comments {
        id
        title
        user {
          id
          email
        }
      }
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Listing 5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of queries to the database, for this scenario, is deliberately identical, but the number of http requests to the API server has been reduced to just one. We argue that the http requests over the Internet are the most costly in this type of application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The backend doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be designed differently to start reaping the benefits of GraphQL, transitioning from REST to GraphQL can be done incrementally. This allows to measure performance improvements and optimize. From this point, the API developer can start to optimize (potentially merge) SQL queries to improve performance. The opportunity for caching is greatly increased, both on the database and API levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstractions on top of SQL (for instance ORM layers) usually have to contend with the &lt;code&gt;n+1&lt;/code&gt; problem. In step &lt;code&gt;4.&lt;/code&gt; of the REST example, a client could have had to request the follower status for the author of each comment in separate requests. This is because in REST there is no standard way of expressing relationships between more that two resources, whereas GraphQL was designed to prevent this problem by using nested queries. Here, we cheat, by fetching all the followers of the user and deferring to the client the logic of determining users who commented and also follow the author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another difference is fetching more data than the client needs, in order to not break the REST resource abstractions. This is important for bandwidth consumption and battery life spent parsing and storing unneeded data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GraphQL is a viable alternative to REST because:
* while it is more difficult to design the API, the process can be done incrementally. For this reason also, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to transition from REST to GraphQL, the two paradigms can coexist without issues.
* it is more efficient in terms of network requests, even with naive implementations like the one in this document. It also offers more opportunities for query optimization and result caching.
* it is more efficient in terms of bandwidth consumption and CPU cycles spent parsing results, because it only returns what is needed to render the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;REST remains very useful if:
* your API is simple, either has a low number of resources or simple relationships between them.
* you already work with REST APIs inside your organization and you have the tooling all set up or your clients expect REST APIs from your organization.
* you have complex ACL policies. In the blog example, a potential feature could allow users to choose which other users can see their email, or their comments on a particular post, or have following be anonymous etc. Optimizing data retrieval and checking complex business rules can be more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appendix-1-graph-databases-and-efficient-data-storage&#34;&gt;Appendix 1: Graph Databases And Efficient Data Storage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is intuitive to think about application domain data as a graph, as this document demonstrates, the question of efficient data storage to support such an interface is still open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years graph databases have become more popular. Deferring the complexity of resolving the request by translating the GraphQL query into a specific graph database query language, seems like a viable solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that graphs are not an efficient data structure compared to relational databases. A vertex can have links to any other vertex in the graph and access patterns are less predictable and thus offer less opportunity for optimization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the problem of caching, ie. which vertices need to be kept in memory for fast access? Generic caching algorithms may not be very efficient in the context of graph traversal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of database sharding: splitting the database into smaller, non-interacting databases, living on separate hardware. In academia, the problem of splitting a graph on the minimal cut is well understood but it is suboptimal and may potentially result in highly unbalanced cuts due to pathological worst-case scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With relational database, data is modeled in records (or rows, or tuples) and columns, tables and database names are simply namespaces. Most databases are row-oriented, which means that each record is a contiguous chunk of memory, all records in a table are neatly packed one after the other on disk (usually sorted by some key column). This is efficient because it optimizes based on the way physical storage works. The most expensive operation for an HDD is to move the read/write head to another sector on the disk, so minimizing these accesses is critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a high probability that, if the application is interested in a particular record, it will need the whole record, not just a single key from it. There is a high probabilty that if the application is interested in a record, it will be interested in it&amp;rsquo;s neighbours as well, for instance a table scan. These two observations make relational databases quite efficient. However, for this reason also, the worst use-case for a relational database is random access across all data all the time. This is exactly what graph databases do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of SSD drives which have faster random access, cheap RAM memory which makes caching large portions of a graph database possible, better techniques to optimize graph caching and partitioning, graph databases have become a viable storage solution. And most large companies use it: Facebook have the Social Graph, Google have the Knowledge Graph.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>